<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dylan Barth</title><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/feeds/general-announcement.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://dylanbarth.com/</id><updated>2016-04-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>0 to 60 in 30 days</title><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/posts/dvorak" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Dylan</name></author><id>tag:dylanbarth.com,2016-04-03:posts/dvorak</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As someone who spends 90% of his workday in front of a computer, a big part of working efficiently is being able to type like an absolute boss. It's a mark of deep dedication and professionalism to be able to sit up straight at your desk, and with not so much as a flicker of your eyes down to your keyboard, let your thoughts flow fluidly through your fingertips and onto your screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growing up with a computer, I felt pretty comfortable typing on a QWERTY keyboard, which is the layout of keys that comes standard with almost every computer or keyboard offering you can buy. I'd heard that there were alternative ways to layout the keys that were more efficient for typing, but I felt fairly complacent in my relationship with QWERTY so I never took the time to look into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I was listening to an &lt;a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2015/02/09/matt-mullenweg/"&gt;interview with Matt Mullenweg&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benevolent_dictator_for_life"&gt;BDFL&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://wordpress.com/"&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt; and founder of &lt;a href="https://automattic.com/"&gt;Automattic&lt;/a&gt;. Among other quirks, Matt is an evangelist for a keyboard layout called Dvorak, which places the most frequently used keys directly underneath the resting position of your fingers. During the interview, he said something that really caught my attention. "... I'm making up the numbers but in a year of typing QWERTY your fingers move like 18 miles and with Dvorak they move 2 miles."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I heard that, my complacency with QWERTY evaporated. I did some quick Googling, and what I read was enough to convince me that Dvorak was worth a try. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;70% of Dvorak keystrokes are in the home row vs only 32% of QWERTY keystrokes. (The home row is where your fingers sit when they are resting on the keyboard.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because of this, Dvorak requires 63% less finger motion than QWERTY!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was also able to find a plethora of anecdotal evidence that switching to Dvorak reduced repetitive strain injury (RSI) symptoms. This tidbit was the tipping point for me, since I spent a few years during college typing like Gollum and developed chronic RSI in my right thumb and wrist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found some arguments against Dvorak as well, but at this point my confirmation bias was working in overdrive. Plus, haters are gonna hate ;) I was off on a mission to learn to type Dvorak!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Dvorak Keyboard Layout" src="/theme/images/dvorak.png" title="The Dvorak keyboard layout" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a company that sold &lt;a href="http://kbcovers.com/dvorak-keyboard-cover"&gt;Mac keyboard covers for Dvorak layouts&lt;/a&gt; and ordered one that would fit my work keyboard for about $30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a feeling that I might have a tough time sticking with the learning process (&lt;em&gt;every single key&lt;/em&gt; except for "A" and "M" change position when you switch between Dvorak and QWERTY!), so I crafted a plan for my Dvorak learning success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, I created social pressure for myself by telling my work colleagues that I was going to switch from QWERTY to Dvorak and that I was going to be the fastest typer in the office. As you can imagine, this instigated a flurry of typing tests. I felt good about myself after I clocked in at a respectable 85 words per minute (WPM). However, a few minutes later, our Head of Content smashed out 119 WPM... It was going to be a long road ahead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second, I created a Google Sheet to track my progress by doing a typing speed test at the end of every day. This would provide a daily check in point and keep me motivated by showing me how far I'd come, especially on days when I felt like I wasn't making any progress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first few days with Dvorak were nothing short of excruciating. I found myself frequently losing my train of thought in the middle of sentences because I had to think on a &lt;em&gt;letter by letter&lt;/em&gt; basis to peck out words. My neck started to throb from the strain of bobbing between looking down at my keyboard and then up at my screen. I honestly noticed a serious drop in my overall satisfaction and sense of well being. My colleagues took notice as well, because I started communicating like a caveman over Slack. When you can barely type, you think hard about what you want to say, or if it's even worth the mental effort at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of day one, I went to do my typing test. 6 WPM. My colleagues just about died laughing. For the rest of that first week, the social pressure was what kept me going. I took my keyboard home with me that weekend and spent about an hour each day working through typing lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My WPM slowly started to tick upward. By the second week, I could type most words without looking down at my keyboard, albeit slowly. I would frequently hit QWERTY keys instead of finding their new place on the Dvorak layout. I felt like if I concentrated hard enough, I could feel my brain rewiring my muscle memory and mental map of the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the third week, I was starting to type with confidence, if not with speed and accuracy. I went all in and ordered three more keyboard covers, one each for my home and work laptops, and one for my wireless home keyboard. Finally, toward the end of week four, I eclipsed the halfway mark -- 60 WPM!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, I've included a chart of my progress that was generated using my Google Sheet tracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A graph of my typing speed over time as I learned dvorak" src="/theme/images/dvorak_chart.png" title="A graph of my typing speed over time as I learned dvorak" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I gave up after a week or two of tracking my QWERTY speed. It felt like I was undoing my progress!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I am only halfway to my ultimate goal of 120 WPM, I wanted to share what I have learned thus far during the process of completely rewiring the typing part of brain, in case any of you have been thinking about trying to make the switch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first few weeks were the toughest, and a combination of social pressure and tracking my progress is what kept me going.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think I would have progressed much faster if I had been more disciplined with my typing lessons. My typing practice was on a "when I can" basis, instead of making time for practice during my daily routine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If could start over, I would probably order touch typing keyboard cover, which has no key labels at all! This would give me the opportunity to try out other alternative keyboard layouts with less friction, and more importantly would break me of my current habit of flicking my eyes down to the keyboard to aid my fingers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was it worth it? Ask me in 40 years when I can (hopefully) still use my fingers and wrists :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://thetypingcat.com/typing-speed-test"&gt;The Typing Cat&lt;/a&gt;: Enjoyable UX for a typing test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://learn.dvorak.nl/"&gt;Dvorak Keyboard Training&lt;/a&gt;: Used for beginner and intermediate practice because it works you from the ground up with real words and it's Dvorak specific.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.keybr.com/#!practice"&gt;Keybr&lt;/a&gt;: Good for practicing capital letters and punctuation -- try importing a Wikipedia page! It also has some interesting, but semi-uninterpretable visualizations for progress tracking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ma.tt/2003/08/on-the-dvorak-keyboard-layout/"&gt;Matt on Dvorak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Data Pipelines with Luigi, Part 2</title><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/posts/luigi_part_2" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Dylan</name></author><id>tag:dylanbarth.com,2015-09-11:posts/luigi_part_2</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title>Data Pipelines with Luigi, Part 1</title><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/posts/luigi_part_1" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Dylan</name></author><id>tag:dylanbarth.com,2015-09-09:posts/luigi_part_1</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title>I Have Faith</title><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/posts/i_have_faith" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan</name></author><id>tag:dylanbarth.com,2013-11-25:posts/i_have_faith</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title>Welcome To The Wild West</title><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/posts/welcome_to_the_wild_west" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan</name></author><id>tag:dylanbarth.com,2013-11-25:posts/welcome_to_the_wild_west</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title>48 Hours to South Sudan</title><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/posts/48_hours_to_south_sudan" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan</name></author><id>tag:dylanbarth.com,2013-11-17:posts/48_hours_to_south_sudan</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title>KA Lite</title><link href="http://dylanbarth.com/posts/kalite" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dylan</name></author><id>tag:dylanbarth.com,2012-12-22:posts/kalite</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;a href="http://khanacademy.org/"&gt;Khan Academy&lt;/a&gt;. To me, it's that band that I listened to way before it became popular and everybody else jumped on the bandwagon. I remember discovering Khan way back in December of 2006, when it was just a YouTube channel and I was a wee little high school sophomore struggling to pay attention in my pre-cal class. At the time, I didn't know how lucky I was to have found those videos. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salman_Khan_(educator)"&gt;Sal&lt;/a&gt; (I call him Sal, because deep down I feel like we're buddies) always managed to break concepts down in such a concise and visually digestible way. If I didn't get it the first time, I could play it over and over again until I understood it without the risk of ridicule. It was a relief. It spurred my interest in the material for the first time. And I remember thinking, "Man… I wish Sal could teach all of my classes."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward 6 years. The Khan Academy has grown into a full-fledged non-profit organization with funding from entities like Google and The Gates Foundation. It has delivered 217,336,268 lessons to date. Anybody with an Internet connection can type http://www.khanacademy.org into their address bar and have instant access to over 3,600 high-quality lessons on topics ranging from Art History and American Civics to Calculus and Computer Programming. How awesome is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's super awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before we throw our hats in the air and do the chicken dance of joy, lets take a closer look at that statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Anybody with an Internet connection can type &lt;a href="http://www.khanacademy.org"&gt;http://www.khanacademy.org&lt;/a&gt; into their address bar and have instant access to over 3,600 high-quality lessons."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait a second. How many people actually have that Internet connection?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do a little digging and you find that the number is actually pretty small. About 35% of the world's population are users of the Internet (&lt;a href="http://www.internetworldstats.com/stats.htm"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;. If you estimate we've got about 7 billion people on this planet, that's about 4,550,000,000 people that are missing out on this party. And if you poke around even more, what you'll find is that it's overwhelmingly people from more-developed countries that have access to the Internet, meaning that the awesome educational resources are only really available to people that probably already have some type of access to a (relatively) quality education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Education is all a matter of building bridges." - Ralph Ellison&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href="http://jamiealexandre.com/"&gt;Jamie Alexandre&lt;/a&gt; of UCSD Cognitive Science fame. Jamie is a super-intelligent vegan-hacker-ninja-Phd student here at UCSD, who never wears the same shirt twice (ok sometimes). Jamie's all about the intersection between learning and technology, and while his research started out in computational linguistics, it has since grown to encompass an astoundingly broad scope, with a focus on online education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Aside: how am I lucky enough to know who this guy is? Well Jamie opens up his lab group to just about anybody on campus who's passionate about learning and making the world a better place. I was fortunate enough to recognize and take advantage of the opportunity to work with Jamie starting around March of 2012).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this past summer Jamie interned as a developer at Khan Academy. You should take the time to read all about his &lt;a href="http://jamiealexandre.com/blog/2012/12/12/what-i-did-at-khan-academy-khanberry-pi-ka-lite/"&gt;awesome experience&lt;/a&gt;, but the important takeaway is that he came back to San Diego with a partially completed web application and a dream: to bring Khan to the 65-70% of the world that is currently off-line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in September of this year, our team of ninjas-in-training plus Jamie got hacking in Jamie's lab (which is a [barely] 10 foot square office with old electronics and research papers scattered everywhere, vegan/Python jokes plastered on the walls, and a white board that has never seen an eraser). It's no lab. It's a hack zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And after 10 weeks of solid work by the entire team (and mostly Jamie), the paint is just starting to dry on the first public launch of [KA Lite](http://kalite.learningequality.org/, a lightweight web app for hosting Khan Academy content from a local server, without the need for an Internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How cool is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If bringing high quality educational content to the rest of the world is important to you, please read more about KA Lite and how you can support the project. I also highly recommend reading what &lt;a href="http://jamiealexandre.com/blog/2012/12/12/ka-lite-offline-khan-academy/"&gt;Jamie has to say&lt;/a&gt; about the project as well as my co-ninja-in-training &lt;a href="http://thisisyourbrainonblogs.wordpress.com/2012/12/13/ka-lite-bringing-education-to-those-who-need-it-most/"&gt;Matt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you happen to be interested in how this experience has affected the thoughts and dreams of a 21 year old, then by all means read a little bit further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Just a little bit about me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year is the last of my undergraduate college career. Like many of my friends, going into this year I had little better than a vague idea of what I'd like to do after graduating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd always secretly dreamed of getting involved with a startup or starting my own company and with my &lt;a href="http://www.cogsci.ucsd.edu/undergraduate-study/major/specializations/#hci"&gt;major and HCI specialization&lt;/a&gt;, I thought I might be able to sneak in the door as a UX guy that could do a little front-end work and was familiar with Django and Rails as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I never considered the idea that someone would actually be crazy enough to pay me to write code. I've just never really been a technical guy. When I decided to learn how to code about 12 months ago, it was just so I could prototype my own ideas and learn enough to have a semi-intelligent conversation with a developer, so that when I took the plunge and started my own thing I would have somewhat of a clue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working on KA Lite these past ten weeks has changed everything for me. Having the chance to work with guys like Jamie, Richard, Matt, and Guan on a regular basis has made me realize that being an engineer is one of the most badass things you could possibly do with your life. In ten weeks, our team was able to build something that will hopefully have a monstrous impact on the quality of education in developing countries. Not to mention that it has turned out to be one of the most fulfilling and fun things I've experienced in my life thus far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still want to start my own company eventually, and I still want to work at a start-up after I graduate, but now I realize that the reason I want to do those things is so that I can have this kind of impact for the rest of my life. I want to be an absolute ninja-hacker web engineer so that I can learn something new every day and build awesome tools that end up making the world a better place to live for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where do I go from here? Well, I know GitHub says I've written a lot of code for KA Lite, but I honestly feel like a total newbie every time I sit down in front of my laptop. I've got about 10 months worth of programming experience (having started last December and with a 2 month break for my summer abroad), so you can imagine that I feel a little late to the party when I hang out with guys who taught themselves Java before their 9th birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the way I look at it, I have a solid six months until graduation in June, which is a good amount of time to go from procedural-thinking clumsy-typer (exaggeration for emphasis) to junior-ninja code-slinging cyber-monkey.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>